Guide to the collection of ARAMCO photographs of oil facilities in Saudi Arabia AD.MC.080
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
ARAMCO photographs of oil facilities in Saudi Arabia
1956-1961
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
AD.MC.080
31 Photographic Prints in 10 folders, approximately 0.10 linear feet.
Photographic prints (31) depicting oil fields, operations, and personnel of the Arabian American Oil Company (ARAMCO) in eastern Saudi Arabia, from 1955-1961. The images were produced by photographers working for ARAMCO.
Conditions governing access
Collection is open for use in the Archives and Special Collections Reading Room, New York University Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate source of acquisition
Acquired by purchase, November 2019.
Arrangement
The photographs in this collection are arranged in folders by the credited photographers name (where identified), and then chronologically.
Content Description
The collection of ARAMCO photographs of oil facilities in Saudi Arabia consists of images created by several photographers working for the Arabian-American Oil Company, or ARAMCO, in the late 1950s and early 1960s, including V.K. Antony, E.E. Seal, T.F. Walters, Khalid Nasr, and Russell Lee, as well as several uncredited photographers. Most of the photographs have credit stamps on the verso of the print, identiying them as "Aramco Photographs" and listing the photographer, but several only have handwritten annotations.
The images depict a number of various facets of ARAMCO's operations at that time, including geological and seismological surveys, drilling operations, gas separating facilities, oil refineries, and shipping terminals, mostly in locations in eastern Saudi Arabia such as Abqaiq, Ain Dar, and Ras Tanura, but also including images from the Rub' al Khali desert. Several images also depict Saudi staff working in various capacities, as well as a couple of images of American personnel, and one image of the Board of Directors of the company seated at a meeting. A few photographs are not identified, and may have been copy prints obtained from other sources, perhaps for use in a planned publication.
While very little is known of the provenance of this group of photographs, the one common feature is that almost all of the prints have an ownership stamp on the verso of Sherry Brown, of Bellingham, Washington. An issue of the company publication "Sun and Flare" identified someone by this name as a child, in a news story about about a youth theatrical production in the late 1950s, and further identified her as the daughter of Dr. Grover F. Brown, the chief agronomist for ARAMCO. All of the photographs have handwritten captions, many of them identifying the location, activities, and people depicted in images, as well as the dates, and it is likely that Ms. Brown could have been the author of these captions.
Petroleum industry and trade -- Saudi Arabia; Petroleum pipelines -- Saudi Arabia; Petroleum refineries -- Saudi Arabia; Rubʻ al-Khali; Arabian American Oil Company
- Photographer: Antony, V.K. (2 images), October - November 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photographer: Seal, E.E., 1956-1962
  - Seismography party in the field; aerial view of a gas-oil separating plant (2 images), September 1956 - November 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Test explosion in field, drilling rig at Ain Dar, refinery at location on Gulf, drilling barge and platform at Manifa, facility at Abqaiq and at Ras Tanura (6 images), November 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Aerial views of tanker terminal and refinery at Ras Tanura (2 images), November 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Saudi drilling crew at Abu Hadriyah field, pipeline at Ras Tanura, hydroformer at unidentified location, Board of Directors seated at table (4 images), 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Photographer: Walters, T.F.
  - Saudi employees in various locations: wharf tender, assisting field geologist, stabilizer operator (4 images), November 1956 - May 1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Rub al Khali drill camp and seismology operations, plus gas lines at Ain Dar (3 images), 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Photographers: various, May 1955 - March 1956, and undated, circa 1960
  - Exploration camps, Saudi oil tanker, and pump station at Ras Tanura (3 images), May 1955 - March 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Children with Saudi fireman, aerial view of Saudi housing development, aerial of camp in Rub al Khali, and Aramco's first refinery, undated, approximately 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Miscellaneous: copy print of historic photograph of signing of Aramco agreement, plus map of Aramco operations in Saudi Arabia (2 images), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)